{"tossups": [{"question": "This man earned respect and a nickname for leading the 1st Continental Light Dragoons, which ambushed John Pyle\u2019s Loyalist militia at the Battle of Haw River. This man\u2019s legion was forced to retreat to Nathanael Greene\u2019s main force at the Battle of Guilford Courthouse after a clash with Banastre Tarleton. George Washington appointed this man to put down the Whiskey Rebellion. For the point, name this Revolutionary War soldier, nicknamed \u201cLight-Horse Harry,\u201d who was the father of a Confederate general.", "answer": "Henry \u201cLight Horse Harry\u201d<b> Lee</b> III (accept Harry<b> Lee</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Hyperbolus argued that this campaign should have included an attack on Carthage. This campaign began as a reply to Segesta\u2019s request for aid, and it was doomed by the arrival of Gylippus\u2019 reinforcements. This campaign received its first setback when the vandalization of the religious hermai statues was falsely blamed on commander Alcibiades [al-kih-bee-ah-deez], prompting him to defect to Sparta. For the point, name this disastrous Peloponnesian War expedition in which Athens attacked an Italian island.", "answer": "<b> Sicilian</b> Expedition (accept descriptions of Athens\u2019 expedition to<b> Sicily</b>; prompt on Peloponnesian War until \u201cSegesta\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This politician names an informal rule that psychiatrists will not speak about politicians\u2019 mental health without analyzing them in person. This politician, who jokingly advocated lobbing a nuclear weapon \u201cinto the men\u2019s room at the Kremlin,\u201d published<em> The Conscience of a Conservative</em> in 1960, four years before his slogan \u201cin your heart, you know he\u2019s right\u201d was mocked by his opponent\u2019s slogan \u201cin your guts, you know he\u2019s nuts.\u201d For the point, name this Arizona senator who lost the 1964 Presidential election to Lyndon Johnson.", "answer": "Barry<b> Goldwater</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Forces loyal to this family consolidated under Mitsunari Ishida to form the Western Army. A member of this family assumed the title of regent because his low birth prevented him from reaching a higher position. The Council of Five Elders was created to rule in place of a young member of this family named Hideyori. Osaka Castle was constructed by a member of this family who wanted to surpass his mentor, Oda Nobunaga. For the point, name this family that opposed Tokugawa Ieyasu [Tokugawa ee-ay-yah-soo] and that included Hideyoshi.", "answer": "<b> Toyotomi</b> clan", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An admiral with this nickname defeated an allied fleet under the command of Andrea Doria at the Battle of Preveza. Another leader with this name ordered the sacking of Milan in 1162 and married Beatrice of Burgundy. An operation with this name superseded Operation Otto as Nazi Germany\u2019s plan for the invasion of the Soviet Union. A king who went by this nickname drowned while crossing the Saleph River during the Third Crusade. For the point, give this nickname of Holy Roman Emperor Frederick I that translates as \u201cRed Beard.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Barbarossa</b> (accept Hayreddin<b> Barbarossa</b>; accept Operation<b> Barbarossa</b>; accept Frederick <b>Barbarossa</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s father convened the Panglong Conference to assess the status of his country\u2019s minorities. Because this woman is the mother of British citizens, she is barred from assuming her elected office. This de facto leader, the head of the National League for Democracy, was not able to accept her Nobel Peace Prize because her country\u2019s military regime had barred her from returning if she left the country. This leader has been criticized for her indifference to the plight of the Rohingya. For the point, name this politician who long opposed the ruling military junta of Myanmar.", "answer": "<b> Aung San Suu Kyi</b> [chee] (prompt on partial answers, as Burmese names do not include surnames)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A leader of this empire fled to Persia after a war with Sher Shah Suri. This empire\u2019s Bengal Subah province accounted for over half of its economic power. As a member of the Navratnas, Birbal advised an illiterate leader of this empire who created his own religion, Din-i Ilahi. The first leader of this empire defeated Ibrahim Lodi at the First Battle of Panipat, which led to the annexation of the Delhi Sultanate. For the point, name this Indian Empire founded by Babur.", "answer": "<b> Mughal</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In one film, this actress portrayed a friend of Simone Beck who accompanies her diplomat husband Paul to Paris. In another film, she portrays a woman who inherits control of her husband\u2019s business after he kills himself in a manic-depressive episode. In that 2017 film, this actress portrayed Katherine Graham, who chooses to publish the<em> Pentagon Papers</em>. For the point, name this actress who played Julia Child in <em>Julie and Julia</em> and who starred in<em> The Post</em>, a three-time Oscar Winner for Best Actress.", "answer": "Meryl<b> Streep</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "The actions of this movement marked the difference between the \u201cpeople of wine\u201d and \u201cpeople of vinegar\u201d according to Yury Tynyanov. The Union of Salvation was an precursor organization to this movement, which used the slogan \u201cKonstantin and Constitution.\u201d Members of this movement were exiled to Siberia after their failed attempt to depose the successor of Alexander I, Nicholas I. For the point, name this movement of reformist Russian officers who executed a failed conspiracy in winter 1825.", "answer": "<b> Decembrist</b>s (accept<b> Decembrist</b> revolt and other additional information; accept<b> pro-Constantine</b> movement and other equivalents before \u201cKonstantin\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The development of Mehrgarh was a direct predecessor to this culture. Deciphering the approximately 400 symbols in this culture\u2019s writing system, including a mysterious unicorn, is an important open question in archaeology. The Great Bath was built by this culture, which possessed the most advanced urban planning and sanitation systems of the ancient world. The docks at Lothal were constructed by this culture, as were the cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-daro. For the point, name this ancient culture that flourished around a namesake Pakistani river.", "answer": "<b> Indus</b> River<b> Valley</b> Civilization (accept<b> Harappa</b>n Civilization before read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Three months prior to this battle, its central location was seized from troops under Martin Perfecto de Cos. Immediately after this battle, the losing side launched a massive retreat called the Runaway Scrape. Susanna Dickinson was one of the few survivors of this battle, which was a two-week siege that claimed the lives of James Bowie and Davy Crockett. For the point, name this 1836 battle in which a San Antonio mission was captured by Santa Anna\u2019s army, inspiring a rallying cry to \u201cRemember\u201d it.", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Alamo</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician made headlines when he received a black eye after relieving himself on the leg of a partygoer at the Sands Point Bath Club in Long Island. This man\u2019s campaigning helped Hattie Wyatt Caraway win a reelection bid as a senator from Arkansas. This man called for radical caps on individual net worth and income in the Share Our Wealth program, but his presidential ambitions ended when he was assassinated by Carl Weiss in 1935. For the point, name this Louisiana politician nicknamed \u201cThe Kingfish.\u201d", "answer": "Huey (Pierce)<b> Long</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a battle in this sea, the ships<em> Iron Duke</em> and<em> Lion</em> were baited into attacking Reinhard Scheer\u2019s fleet. In this sea, the<em> Ariadne</em> was sunk and admiral Leberecht Maas was killed when a naval squadron was ambushed near Heligoland Bight. John Jellicoe and Franz Hipper\u2019s Royal Navy and High Seas Fleet faced off at the World War I Battle of Jutland in, for the point, what sea located between Britain, Scandinavia, and Germany?", "answer": "<b> North</b> Sea", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Precise masonry practiced by this culture allowed them to build a wall containing a stone cut with twelve angles and sides. A city built by this culture was possibly laid out in the shape of a puma. This culture built a large sundial-like structure known as the<em> intihuana</em> in another city built for Emperor Pachachuti; that site was was discovered by an expedition led by Hiram Bingham. For the point, name this Andean empire that built Machu Picchu.", "answer": "<b> Inca</b> Empire (or<b> Inca</b>ns)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s husband was killed by a gunpowder explosion that leveled a house at Kirk o\u2019 Field. This woman\u2019s betrothal was provided by the Treaty of Greenwich [gren-itch], and her marriage to Edward VI was the goal of the aggressors in the War of the Rough Wooing. After the suspicious death of her husband, Lord Darnley, this person was imprisoned by her cousin Elizabeth I and held in captivity until her execution. For the point, name this queen whose nickname reflects her rule over a realm north of England.", "answer": "<b> Mary, Queen of Scots</b> (accept<b> Mary Stuart</b>; accept<b> Mary I of Scotland</b>; prompt on Mary or Mary I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Fighting in this country, which fought the Sand War with Morocco, caused the Harkis and Pied Noirs [peed-nwah] to flee to Europe. The Evian Accords ended a war of independence in, for the point, what former colonial holding of France in North Africa?", "answer": "<b> Algeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was nicknamed the \u201cmineral water drinking\u201d secretary after taxing and restricting the sale of alcohol. This man, who suppressed rebels in Baku during Black January, began a policy of allowing satellite states to manage their internal affairs that earned the nickname \u201cSinatra Doctrine.\u201d After serving as this man\u2019s Vice President, Gennady Yanayev led a Gang of Eight coup against him that failed after Boris Yeltsin stood on a tank. The policies of glasnost and perestroika were created by, for the point, what last General Secretary of the Soviet Union?", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author asked \u201cWhat is it fateful woman... Are the things so strange and marvelous you see or have seen?\u201d in his poem \u201cEthiopia Saluting the Colours.\u201d An army hospital is the setting of this man\u2019s poem \u201cThe Wound Dresser,\u201d which joins a poem that declares \u201cBeat! beat! drums!-blow! bugles! blow!\u201d in his collection<em> Drum-Taps</em>. This author stated \u201cour fearful trip is done\u201d in a poem about the assassination of Abraham Lincoln. For the point, name this American author of \u201cO Captain! My Captain!\u201d and<em> Leaves</em> <em>of Grass</em>.", "answer": "Walt<b> Whitman</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man met with Nikita Khrushchev in an outdoor pool and, exploiting Khrushchev\u2019s poor swimming, humiliatingly offered him water wings. Pakistan\u2019s foreign minister inadvertently caused a mass hysteria by presenting mangoes to this man. Enver Hoxha [ho-cha] was the only leader to support this man in a decade-long political struggle over de-Stalinization. For the point, name this Chinese leader who oversaw the Sino-Soviet split and whose sayings are collected in the \u201cLittle Red Book.\u201d", "answer": "Chairman<b> Mao</b> Zedong (or<b> Mao</b> Tse-tung)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A former president noted that this legislation \u201cawakened and filled me with terror\u201d \u201clike a firebell in the night.\u201d Directly prior to this legislation, the Senate rejected the Tallmadge Amendment. This legislation prevented slavery in territories north of the 36-30 parallel, and admitted Maine as a free state in exchange for a namesake territory being admitted as a slave state. The Kansas-Nebraska Act nullified, for the point, what controversial 1820 compromise?", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b> Compromise <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A palace in this city is filled with paintings commemorating victory over the Ottomans at the Battle of Cesme [chez-mah]. The largest stone ever moved by man, the Thunderstone, was transported to this city, where it now serves as a pedestal for a bronze equestrian statue of this city\u2019s modernizing founder. Swamps on the Neva River were cleared out to construct this \u201cwindow to the west.\u201d For the point, name this city that was built to replace Moscow as the capital of Russia.", "answer": "<b> St. Petersburg</b> (accept<b> Petrograd</b> or<b> Leningrad</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}], "bonuses": []}